<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-zhang-dmsc-mas-communication-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="">Security Analysis of Multi-agents Secured Communication
    and Limitations of Existing Protocols</title>

    <author fullname="Haodi Zhang" initials="H." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Tangxia Street, Tianhe District</street>

          <city>Guangzhou</city>

          <region>Guangzhou</region>

          <code>510000</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>zhanghaodi@chinatelecom.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="16" month="January" year="2026"/>

    <area>IETF Area</area>

    <workgroup>DMSC Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Dynamic Multi-agents, Secured Communication</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Multi-agents systems (MAS) increasingly cooperate through workflow,
      orchestrated, and mesh communication patterns. While existing Internet
      protocols provide confidentiality and endpoint authentication, they were
      not designed for agent-native semantics such as dynamic identity,
      computation-bounded requests, context integrity, and intermediary trust.
      This document analyzes security risks in agent communication and
      identifies limitations in widely deployed protocols (TLS, HTTP, MQTT,A2A
      and etc.) and developer framework (AutoGen and etc.). This document
      intend to establish a common problem statement and gap analysis to
      inform future IETF standardization.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>AI agents are autonomous software entities capable of interacting
      with other agents, tools, and services to perform multi-step reasoning
      and task execution. Emerging MAS are deployed across heterogeneous
      infrastructures, often spanning administrative domains. Current Internet
      security mechanisms primarily protect communication channels and
      endpoints. However, they do not fully address agent-specific security
      semantics, including dynamic identity, workload-based abuse, semantic
      context integrity, and trust in intermediaries. This document provides:
      <xref target="IoA"/>.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A brief threat analysis of agent communication based on
          collaboration patterns.</t>

          <t>A classification of core security risks.</t>

          <t>A gap analysis highlighting the limitations of protocols and
          developer framework.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The scope of this document focuses on communication security for
      distributed AI agents, including:Agent-to-Agent (A2A),
      Agent-to-Orchestrator (A2O), Agent-to-Tool/Service (A2T). It does not
      cover model training security, data governance, or ethical issues.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions used in this document">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">
      </xref> .</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The following terms are defined in <xref target="architecture"/>
      .</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Agent: An autonomous software entity capable of perception,
          planning, decision-making, and execution.</t>

          <t>DMSC: Dynamic Multi-agent Secured Collaboration. The framework
          and infrastructure enabling secure and efficient collaboration among
          dynamic agents.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Core Communication Security Risks in MAS">
      <t>MAS orchestration mechanisms include three primary patterns<xref
      target="IoA"/>: Workflows rely on predefined, linear, or conditional
      task sequences, exhibiting predictable sequential control flows and a
      pipeline topology; Hierarchical Planning utilizes a centralized
      orchestrator for task decomposition and intelligent routing, resulting
      in a star or tree topology with highly concentrated control and decision
      authority; and Multi-Agent Collaboration features a decentralized,
      peer-to-peer architecture where agents interact dynamically within a
      mesh or swarm topology, distributing both control flow and
      decision-making capabilities.</t>

      <t>From a security perspective, workflows face risks primarily related
      to context integrity, as communication is limited to adjacent agents,
      making the system vulnerable to payload injection or corruption despite
      clear identity boundaries. Hierarchical Planning presents significant
      Single Point of Failure (SPOF) and Man-in-the-Middle (MITM) risks due to
      its centralized nature; a compromise of the orchestrator can lead to
      global impact, necessitating End-to-End Encryption (E2EE) and
      agent-payload binding. Meanwhile, Multi-Agent Collaboration,
      characterized by fuzzy identity and trust boundaries, is susceptible to
      computational Denial of Service (DoS) attacks as well as context
      injection and pollution, requiring strict peer-level identity
      validation, context signing, and workload control.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Identity and Trust Boundaries</t>
        </list>Agent-based systems rely on dynamically instantiated,
      short-lived entities whose identities are often assigned at runtime.
      Unlike traditional services, agents do not map cleanly to long-lived
      hosts, domains, or organizational identities. In collaborative or mesh
      topologies, agents may be created, delegated, or terminated on demand,
      and may act on behalf of other agents or users. This introduces identity
      ambiguity and weak trust binding: it becomes unclear who an agent
      represents, what authority it has, and whether its identity is stable
      over time.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Context Integrity and Semantic Consistency</t>
        </list>Agent communication is not limited to stateless requests; it
      often carries evolving conversational state, task context, intermediate
      reasoning artifacts, and shared memory objects. While transport-layer
      security can protect messages in transit, it does not ensure that the
      semantic context remains intact across multiple hops, intermediaries, or
      storage layers. In workflows and collaborative meshes alike, context can
      be truncated, reordered, injected, or selectively modified without
      cryptographic detection. This creates risks of context poisoning,
      instruction injection, and silent manipulation of agent reasoning
      processes.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Orchestrator and Broker Trust</t>
        </list>In hierarchical and brokered architectures, a central
      orchestrator or message broker mediates most or all communications. This
      entity becomes a single point of failure and a powerful trust anchor. If
      compromised, misconfigured, or simply overly privileged, the
      orchestrator can inspect, modify, suppress, or replay messages between
      agents. Even when transport security is used, the orchestrator typically
      terminates connections and therefore has full access to plaintext. This
      introduces MITM risks and undermines E2E security guarantees.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Unpredictable Workload and Resource Exhaustion</t>
        </list>Agent interactions frequently involve expensive computation
      such as large-model inference, retrieval-augmented generation, or tool
      execution. In collaborative and mesh settings, any peer may request
      high-cost operations from another agent. Existing protocols do not
      account for computational asymmetry between requester and responder, nor
      do they provide mechanisms to express, negotiate, or enforce resource
      budgets. As a result, agents are vulnerable to DoS attacks that exploit
      legitimate-looking but computationally expensive tasks.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Architectural Amplification of Risk</t>
        </list>The above risks manifest differently across communication
      patterns. In sequential workflows, the primary concerns are identity
      binding and preservation of task context across hops. In orchestrated
      systems, central control amplifies risks of message manipulation and
      single points of failure. In decentralized collaboration, dynamic peer
      discovery and many-to-many communication exacerbate identity ambiguity,
      context pollution, and DoS exposure. Together, these patterns
      demonstrate that agent communication security is not merely a transport
      problem, but an architectural and semantic one.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Limitations of Existing Protocols in Addressing Agent Communication Security">
      <t>This section analyzes why commonly used communication protocols and
      frameworks&mdash;specifically TLS, HTTP/gRPC, the A2A protocol, and
      AutoGen&mdash;do not adequately mitigate the risks identified in Section
      4. As highlighted in <xref
      target="architecture">draft-li-dmsc-inf-architecture-01</xref>,
      multi-agent systems require network infrastructures to support
      agent-centric identity management, capability-aware communication, and
      cross-domain collaboration&mdash;requirements that existing protocols
      fail to address, leading to resource exhaustion risks. The focus is not
      on implementation flaws, but on structural gaps between protocol
      assumptions and the requirements of agent-based systems.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Inadequate Support for Dynamic Agent Identity</t>
        </list>TLS, HTTP/gRPC with OAuth or TLS authentication mechanisms bind
      identity to endpoints, certificates, or client identifiers. These
      constructs assume relatively stable entities such as servers, users, or
      devices. They do not natively support ephemeral, software-defined agents
      that are created on demand, act under delegated authority, or represent
      composite roles. While the A2A protocol introduces explicit AgentID
      fields, these identifiers are transmitted without mandatory
      cryptographic binding to trust anchors, delegation chains, or verifiable
      credentials. In AutoGen, agent identity is typically managed at the
      application layer using tokens or configuration files, lacking
      standardized, interoperable identity semantics. Consequently, none of
      these protocols provide a robust mechanism to express who an agent is,
      whom it represents, and under what authority it operates.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Lack of End-to-End Context Protection</t>
        </list>Existing protocols prioritize transport security rather than
      message-level or context-level integrity. TLS ensures confidentiality
      and integrity only between adjacent endpoints; once a message is
      decrypted, any intermediary, broker, or application layer can modify the
      payload without detection. HTTP/gRPC similarly protect the channel but
      do not require payload signing or semantic validation. A2A defines
      structured message objects but does not mandate E2E encryption or
      cryptographic signing of context elements. AutoGen inherits the
      properties of its underlying transports, with no built-in enforcement of
      message or context integrity. As a result, none of these systems can
      guarantee that conversational state, instructions, or task context have
      not been altered across multiple hops.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Over-Privileged Orchestrators and Brokers</t>
        </list>In orchestrated and brokered architectures, existing protocols
      implicitly assume that the intermediary is fully trusted. TLS
      termination at a gateway, HTTP reverse proxies, MQTT brokers, and agent
      orchestrators in both A2A-based and AutoGen systems all have access to
      plaintext messages. This means that the orchestrator or broker can
      become an undetectable MITM, contradicting the distributed trust
      assumptions often made in multi-agent designs.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Absence of Computation-Aware Communication Controls</t>
        </list>None of the evaluated protocols incorporate concepts of
      computational cost, resource budgeting, or workload fairness. A request
      that triggers a trivial database lookup and one that initiates a
      multi-step reasoning chain over a large language model are treated
      identically at the protocol level. MQTT quality-of-service levels ensure
      delivery semantics, not execution cost. A2A and AutoGen allow agents to
      request complex tasks from peers without standardized mechanisms to
      declare, negotiate, or enforce limits on CPU, memory, inference time, or
      external tool usage. This structural blind spot leaves agents vulnerable
      to resource exhaustion attacks that appear legitimate at the message
      layer.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Mismatch Between Agent Architectures and Protocol Assumptions</t>
        </list>Collectively, TLS, HTTP/gRPC and MQTT were designed around
      service-oriented or message-oriented paradigms in which endpoints are
      relatively stable, intermediaries are trusted, and payload semantics are
      outside the protocol&rsquo;s scope. Agent-based systems violate these
      assumptions: identities are fluid, trust is contextual and delegated,
      messages carry evolving semantic state, and computation itself becomes
      an attack surface. The result is a systematic gap: even when these
      protocols are correctly implemented, they cannot provide the E2E
      identity assurance, context integrity, intermediary minimization, and
      resource-aware controls required for secure multi-agent
      communication.</t>
    </section>

    <section title=" Conclusion">
      <t>This document focuses on the communication security of multi-agent
      systems, systematically identifying critical gaps between existing
      communication protocols (such as TLS, HTTP/gRPC, MQTT, A2A, and AutoGen)
      and the security requirements of dynamic agent networks. Key issues
      identified include inadequate support for ephemeral and dynamic agent
      identities, lack of E2E semantic context protection, over-privileged
      intermediaries (brokers/orchestrators) leading to MITM risks, absence of
      computation-aware communication controls that render agents vulnerable
      to DoS attacks, and architectural amplification of these risks across
      different collaboration patterns (workflows, hierarchical planning, and
      decentralized mesh collaboration). Collectively, these gaps demonstrate
      that secure communication in multi-agent systems is not merely a
      transport-layer problem but a systematic challenge involving identity
      semantics, context integrity, and resource management.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document suggests that secure agent communication requires a new
      class of protocol capabilities that extend beyond traditional network
      and application-layer security. These include: (1) agent identity
      semantics that support ephemeral and delegatable identities independent
      of hosts or domains; (2) computation-aware communication mechanisms that
      allow agents to declare, negotiate, and enforce resource consumption
      limits, mitigating high-cost request abuse; (3) semantic context
      protection, through mandatory signing and optional encryption of
      payloads and context windows to preserve integrity across multiple hops;
      and (4) end-to-end trust in mediated topologies, enabling brokers or
      orchestrators to route messages without accessing or modifying their
      contents. Together, these directions outline a path for future
      standardization: defining agent-aware identity and delegation models,
      specifying message- and context-level security envelopes, and
      integrating resource governance into communication protocols. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <reference anchor="IoA">
        <front>
          <title>Securing-Agentic-Applications-Guide-1.0</title>

          <author fullname="Idan Habler" initials="H." surname="Idan">
            <organization>OWASP</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="28" month="July" year="2025"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="architecture">
        <front>
          <title>draft-li-dmsc-inf-architecture-01</title>

          <author fullname="Xueting Li" initials="X." surname="Li">
            <organization>China Telecom</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Junai Wang" initials="A." surname="W">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date day="9" month="January" year="2026"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
